A Guide to the Loudoun's Quilt of Faith, 2008-
Thomas Balch Library
Thomas Balch Library
Loudoun's Quilt of Faith 2008-
Thomas Balch Library
M 042 - VC 0020
.85 cu. ft. (15 churches)
Loudoun's Quilt of Faith, an inter-faith oral history project begun in 2008, explores the importance of religion in the lives of Loudoun County residents. The collection includes digital and print photographs, digitized interviews, and church brochures.
Christopher Stevenson
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection open for research.
Acquisition Information
Christopher Stevenson, Purcellville, Virginia
Alternative Form Available
Digital images
Accruals
2008.0141, 2008.0145, 2008.0156, 2008.0179, 2008.0193, 2009.0001, 2009.0052, 2009.0065, 2009.0099, 2009.0113, 2009.0164, 2010.0003, 2010.0154, 2010.0195
Historical Information
Loudoun's Quilt of Faith, an inter-faith oral history project begun in 2008, explores the importance of religion in the lives of Loudoun County residents. Conceptualized as part of a national oral history project, America's Quilt of Faith, Loudoun's Quilt of Faith is currently the only active component. Project founder and Loudoun County resident Christopher Stevenson, a physicist, teacher, and engineer by training, was inspired by what he sees as the exceptional role religion played, and continues to play, in the cultural and political life of the United States.
Stevenson points to the United States of America's unique religious experience as fundamental in allowing the emergence of America's twenty-first century religious landscape. He also sees the United States' religious experience as markedly different from the rest of the world -- both advanced and developing nations -- where absence of practicing faith and/or lack of tolerance and religious diversity are hallmarks.
Building on the survey work of institutions like the Pew Forum on Religion and Public Life and the 2008 American Religious Identification Survey, Stevenson seeks to capture a snapshot of the diversity of the American religious experience in a narrative format. He developed a template of twenty-eight questions, ranging from salvation and sin to evangelism to the role of religion in revitalizing American families, to which both leaders and congregants of religious communities were asked to respond. These interviews were digitally audio-recorded. In addition, Stevenson and photographer Kim Graham and Heather Lindsey attended worship services, during which Graham photographed congregations actively practicing their faith.
Scope and Content
The collection includes digital and print photographs, digitized interviews, and church brochures. It is an open collection; additional materials will be added as they are completed.
Completed:
Bethany United Methodist Church, Purcellville
St. Francis de Sales Catholic Church, Purcellville
St. James Episcopal Church, Leesburg
St. Peter's Episcopal Church, Purcellville
King of Kings Worship Center, Purcellville
Northern Virginia Baha'i Center, Sterling
All Dulles Area Muslim Society (ADAMS), Sterling
Abundant Life Church of God, Hamilton
Hamilton Baptist Church, Hamilton
Hamilton Ward - Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-Day Saints, Hamilton
Second Mount Olive Baptist Church, Hamilton
Unitarian Universalists of Sterling, Sterling
Leesburg Church of the Nazarene, Leesburg
Greek Orthodox Parish of Loudoun County, Dulles
Grace Annex United Methodist Church, Purcellville
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Bibliography
America's Quilt of Faith, http://www.americasquiltoffaith.org/index.html, accessed 15 September 2008.
Stevenson, Christopher, interview and correspondence with Beth Schuster, September, 2008
Other Finding Aid
Past Perfect catalogue records for photographs
Technical Requirements
Electronic media
Contents List
- (Box 1)
  - Website printout, 15 September 2008
  - Bethany United Methodist Church, Purcellville -- church information and bulletins, June 2008
  - Bethany United Methodist Church, Purcellville -- releases and photo list, June 2008
  - St.James Episcopal Church, Leesburg -- church information and bulletins, June 2008
  - St.James Episcopal Church, Leesburg -- church information, June 2008
  - St.James Episcopal Church, Leesburg -- releases and photo list, June 2008
  - St. Peter's Episcopal Church, Purcellville -- church information and bulletins, August 2008
  - St. Peter's Episcopal Church, Purcellville -- photo list, August 2008
  - St. Francis de Sales Catholic Church, Purcellville -- church information and bulletins, June-August 2008
  - St. Francis de Sales Catholic Church, Purcellville -- releases and photo list, November 2008
  - King of Kings Worship Center, Purcellville -- church information, n.d.
  - King of Kings Worship Center, Purcellville -- releases and photo list, December 2008
  - Northern Virginia Baha'i Center, Sterling -- church information, n.d.
  - Northern Virginia Baha'i Center, Sterling -- releases and photo list, November 2008
  - All Dulles Area Muslim Society (ADAMS), Sterling -- church information, n.d.
  - All Dulles Area Muslim Society (ADAMS), Sterling -- releases and photo list, February 2009
  - Abundant Life Church of God, Hamilton -- church information, n.d.
  - Hamilton Abundant Life Church of God, Hamilton -- releases, no photo list, February 2009
  - Hamilton Baptist Church, Hamilton -- church information, n.d.
  - Hamilton Baptist Church, Hamilton -- releases and photo list, March 2009
  - Hamilton Ward -- Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-Day Saints, Hamilton -- church information, n.d.
  - Hamilton Ward -- Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-Day Saints, Hamilton -- releases and photo list, April 2009
  - Second Mount Olive Baptist Church, Hamilton -- church information, September 2009
  - Second Mount Olive Baptist Church, Hamilton -- releases and photo list, June 2009
  - Unitarian Universalists of Sterling, Sterling -- church information, May 2009
  - Unitarian Universalists of Sterling, Sterling -- releases, no photo list, May 2009
  - Leesburg Church of the Nazarene, Leesburg -- church information, October 2009
  - Leesburg Church of the Nazarene, Leesburg -- releases and photo list, October 2009
  - Greek Orthodox Parish of Loudoun County, Dulles -- church information, September 2009
  - Greek Orthodox Parish of Loudoun County, Dulles -- releases and photo list, September 2009
  - Grace Annex United Methodist Church, Purcellville -- church information, January 2009
  - Grace Annex United Methodist Church, Purcellville -- releases and photo list, n.d.
- (VC 0020)
  - Bethany United Methodist Church, Purcellville, 29 June 2008
  - St.James Episcopal Church, Leesburg, 8 June 2008
  - St. Peter's Episcopal Church, Purcellville, August 2008
  - St. Francis de Sales Catholic Church, November 2008
  - King of Kings Worship Center, Purcellville, December 2008
  - Northern Virginia Baha'i Center, Sterling, November 2009
  - All Dulles Area Muslim Society, Sterling, February 2009
  - Abundant Life Church of God, Hamilton, February 2009
  - Hamilton Baptist Church, Hamilton, March 2009
  - Hamilton Ward -- Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-Day Saints, Hamilton, April 2009
  - Unitarian Universalists of Sterling, Sterling, May 2009
  - Second Mount Olive Baptist Church, Hamilton, November 2009
  - Greek Orthodox parish of Loudoun County, Dulles, September 2009
- (AV 001)
  - Bethany United Methodist Church, Purcellville -- pastor interview, part 1, 24 June 2008
  - Bethany United Methodist Church, Purcellville -- pastor interview, part 2, 24 June 2008
  - Bethany United Methodist Church, Purcellville -- congregation interviews, 29 June 2008
  - Bethany United Methodist Church, Purcellville -- photographs, 29 June 2008
  - Hamilton Baptist Church, Hamilton -- service, March 2009
  - Hamilton Ward -- Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-Day Saints, Hamilton -- oral histories, April 2009
  - Hamilton Ward -- Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-Day Saints, Hamilton -- photographs, April 2009
  - Second Mount Olive Baptist Church -- photographs, June 2009
  - Second Mount Olive Baptist Church -- photographs, November 2009
  - Leesburg Church of the Nazarene -- group interviews and photographs
  - Greek Orthodox Parish of Loudoun County -- interviews and photographs
  - Grace Annex United Methodist Church -- interviews and photographs
  - St. James Episcopal Church, Leesburg -- interviews and photographs, 8 June 2008, 16 June 2008, 14 September 2008
  - St. Peter's Episcopal Church, Purcellville -- interviews and photographs, August 2008
  - St. Francis de Sales Catholic Church, Purcellville -- interviews and photographs, June-November 2008
  - King of Kings Worship Center, Purcellville -- interviews and photographs, December 2008
  - Northern Virginia Baha'i Center, Sterling -- interviews and photographs, November 2008
  - All Dulles Area Muslim Society (ADAMS) -- interviews and photographs, February 2009
  - Abundant Life Church of God -- interviews and photographs, February 2009
  - Hamilton Baptist Church -- interviews and photographs, March 2009
  - Second Mount Olive Baptist Church -- pastor interview, February 2009
  - Unitarian Universalists of Sterling -- pastor interviews, March 2009
  - Leesburg Church of the Nazarene -- interviews and photographs, n.d